Inventory of the William Meade Papers 1807-1861
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence, 1841-1850., 43 items. (Box 1-2)
  - W[illiam] Meade, Mecklenburg, [Virginia], to Mary Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 17 June [18]44., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Notes the activities of the household of which Meade is a guest; believes that his health is improving because of "unusually cool summer;" sends greetings to all at home.
  - [Dr.] Henry W. Ducachet, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Rt. Rev. William Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 22 Feb[ruary] 1845., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Expresses gratitude to Meade for the "moral courage you have manifested in bringing a most unworthy man to justice"; adds approval that those of the accused's ilk are at their "downfall."
  - William Meade, Suffolk, [Virginia], to the Minister and Vestry of the Episcopal Church in Suffolk, [Virginia], 25 April 1845., 2 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Congratulates them on the commencement of building a new church; warns them, however, not to give the altar the central position to the detriment of the lectionary and pulpit; encourages them to maintain peace in the Virginia diocese by designing the church according to the custom of that area and not returning, as apparently some were doing, to the "Romish forms."
  - J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth [Virginia], to Rt. Rev. W[illiam] Meade, Fredericksburg, Virginia, 19 May 1845., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Informs Meade of the case of one in Wingfield's church who voluntarily withdrew himself from communion and was then elected a delegate to the state convention; Wingfield thinks that to attend convention he ought to commune.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Alexandria, [Virginia], to anonymous correspondent, 27 Ju[ne][18]45., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Regrets that correspondent should think that Meade questioned [or doubted] the correspondent's conscientiousness and conveyed these doubts to a Dr. Waller [?].
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to R. B. Butt [?] and other members of the Vestry ..., Portsmouth, Virginia, 5 August [18]45., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Regrets the continuing conflict between rector and vestrymen; advises that granting an associate rectorship would be contrary to custom; argues from this one unless size demarked it; encourages them to heal the breaches.
  - William [Meade], Millwood, [Virginia], to General Cochran, n.p., 18 January 1845., 5 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Relates that he had earlier decided to abstain from all distilled liquors; sometimes drinks a domestic wine mixed with water; supports the Temperance Societies but opposes their demands for total abstinence, arguing that there is liberty to drink wine in moderation; believes total abstinence is best for some, but that it shouldn't be insisted upon; youth should abstain; notes that intemperance in eating and drinking are often connected; some eat excessively to have an excuse for drinking; had wine been as strong in the "time of the Prophets and Apostles," Scripture may have forbidden its use.
    Including TCy of L. 8 pages.
  - [Rev. J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia] to [William Meade], n.p., [post 8 June 1846]., 4 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Quotes extensively from a document of one of the vestrymen friendly to both parties [Wingfield and the opposing vestry] in which the writer exhorts both sides to lay aside differences, to act charitably, to be in proper subjection to their minister, and not to be so quick to judge; Wingfield then quotes from Murdough who rejected the counsel of charitability and cites remaining differences; Wingfield asserts that no congregation can "gag" him or keep him from preaching "the whole counsel of God."
  - Rev. J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia, to Rt. Rev. William Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 21 Dec[ember] 1846., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Wingfield, having been called a "high churchman, [and] Romanist" by some in his congregation, denies the charges and assures Meade that it is those laymen who are of "sectarian descent" and revival converts that are acting uncharitably; takes Meade to task for earlier referring favorably to the dissenters and continues to excoriate his attackers in strong terms; asks Meade to state in writing if he knows of anything heretical in W.'s preaching or immoral in his conduct; to undercut W.; feels that his entire "official life is at stake;" pleads for Meade's Judgment.
  - Rev. J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia, to Rt. Rev. William Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 5 [or] 6 Jan[uar]y 1847., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Begs apology for attributing a phrase to Meade which he never used in referring to the disgruntled vestryman of W's church; asks that the charges these members have sent to Meade be sent to W. expresses surprise that five vestrymen registered dissatisfaction.
  - William Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Rev. J. H. Wingfield, [Portsmouth, Virginia], 11 January 1847., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Assures Wingfield of his continued personal regard for him; relates to Wingfield his correspondence with the dissatisfied vestry and reports a few of their objections, such as W's serving of communion on Saint's days; explains that if he were to ignore the complaints as W. wished him to that he would rightly be accused of disregarding the wishes of vestry and congregation; warns him that if the one of his recent letters are an indication, that W. seems open to the charge of imprudence and harshness;" chastens him for his ultraistic views and exhorts him not to count as un-Christian any merely because they are not Episcopalian; in a post script, notes that Bp. John has declined to handle the matter and that Meade will ask the vestry for a complete list of the charges.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood [Virginia], to Rev. J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia, 11 Jan[uar]y 1847., 7 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - W[illiam] Mead[sic], Millwood, Virginia, to Dr. Bates[sic] and others of the Vestry of the Episcopal Church, Portsmouth, [Virginia], 14 January [18]47., 1 page. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Informs them of Bp. John's referral of the disputed matters back to him; asks the vestry to give him a complete list of the charges against Wingfield.
  - Rev. J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, [Virginia], to Right Rev. William Meade, n.p., 28[?], Jan[uar]y 1847., 12 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Acknowledges that Meade has indeed extended countless kindnesses towards him in the past; accuses Meade of encouraging the opposing vestry; quotes long extract for sermon, answering charge that he believed non-Episcopalians not to be Christian; rather argues that the Episcopal Church is the only true church, while still not rejecting the salvation of those truly pious ones outside the church; heaps further abuse on the heads of his opponents; claims that his stand for the Episcopal Church is the true one and makes an appeal to God and conscience; begs to be forgiven of anything offensive, but affirms to know of not other means of defense than those which he has employed.
  - [William Meade], n.p. to J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia, 13 March 1847., 6 pages. AL. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Argues that the sometimes harsh tone of the Meade-Wingfield correspondence was set by the tone of Wingfield's first letter; reasserts the right of the laity to question a minister; concludes that since Wingfield appears established in his high church views "that there is so little prospect of any good resulting from [Meade's] efforts;" in the meeting which Meade conducted between Wingfield and the vestry, Wingfield apparently afterwards claimed that sermon quotes attributed to him had been misrepresented.
  - [William Meade], Millwood, [Virginia], to Dr. Watts, Mr. Murdough, and others, [Portsmouth, Virginia], 14 March 1847., 3 pages. L. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Declares that he has done all he can to foster understanding between vestry and minister; claims that he can offer no further advice or hope of healing the breach; encourages them not to be overly-critical of Rev. Wingfield.
  - [Rev.] J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia to Right Rev. W[illia]m Meade, Fairfax County, Virginia, 26 April 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Explains that one who had earlier offended Wingfield had explained behaviour, but that this person and eleven others withdrew from his church when the congregation voted 3 to 1 to expel the disgruntled vestrymen. These members now take communion in another parish; wants to know whether these members can legitimately be under the ministration of another while residing in his parish.
  - W[illiam] Meade n.p., to Rev. J. H. Wingfield, [Portsmouth, Virginia], 10 May 1947., 3 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Explains that if the laity in a town of several parishes can chose which one to attend, that a country parish should afford the same convenience; argues that worship is not merely a matter of convenience, and that it is unsafe and unwise to try to prevent members from attending the parish of their choice; tells Wingfield to be grateful that those who disturbed him are gone.
  - W[illiam] Meade, "Mountain View," [Millwood, Virginia], to Rev. W. Jones, Millwood [Virginia], 22 August 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Advises him to seize the opportunity which Providence has provided, resign his Virginia parish, and accept an appointment in Memphis, [Tennessee].
  - [William Meade], [ca 1847]., 1 page. AMs. (Box-folder 2:1)
    [Endorsement reads], "Sketch of advise which Bishop Meade had it in his mind to give to Rev. W. G. H. Jones and to which he refers in a letter to him. It does not appear that it was given." Advises to avoid "controversy, raising doubts, arguing"; urges caution in speech, and regularity in parochial visits.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Rev. J. H. Wingfield, Portsmouth, Virginia, 29 August [18]47., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Expresses dissatisfaction with the tone of some of Wingfield's language used in an earlier letter.
  - W[illiam Meade], [Dec. 1847]., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Declares that vestryman Briswell [?] told him of [Rev. Mr. Jones's] resignation and wondered whether he had really secured a position in Memphis. Meade said that he had seen the Memphis letter offering him [Jones] the minister's position; Meade notes at bottom that he wrote this because Mr. Jones thought Meade's reply affirming that he had seen Jones's letter induced the vestry to accept Jones's resignation.
  - William Meade, [account of conversations with minister, Rev. W. J. H. Jones, and vestry of parish church, Millwood, Virginia], 23 Decem[ber] 1847., 4 pages. AD. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Jones had earlier considered threatening resignation, hoping that the vestry would raise his salary; Meade told him that instead the vestry would accept his resignation; when he finally offered resignation after having secured a position in Memphis, a polite but insincere pleas on the part of some for him to stay almost induced Jones to stay; Meade encouraged him, once again, to leave.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to [Rev. W. G. H. Jones], n.p., 27 Decem[ber] [18]47., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Wishes Jones well as he departs Millwood and regrets the misunderstandings between them.
  - W[illiam] Meade n.p., to Dr. R. C. Randolph, n.p., 27 December 1847., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Explains his reasons for opposing [Rev.] Hutchinson's appointment [at Millwood, Virginia] and that it was not because of any personal ill-will.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Rev. W. Hutchinson, n.p., 1 January 1848., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    The document was apparently enclosed with the letter; when Hutchinson's name was mentioned as a successor to the recently resigned Millwood parish rector, Meade expresses disapproval because Hutchinson's wife has a number of relatives in the congregation; notes that about fifteen parishes have ministers with close personal ties and that it is not a good arrangement; assures Hutchinson that he has no personal ill regard for him but that he is especially concerned since Millwood is Meade's home parish.
    Including AD re: Case of Thomas Hutchinson, written by Meade testifying to the documents veracity. 4 pages.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Alexandria, [Virginia], to [Rev. James Craik, Louisville, Kentucky]. 9 May 1850., 3 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Expresses pleasure over Craik's recent work on baptismal regeneration and notes that Craik's position is that of the Reformers; takes exception with Craik's restricted use of the word "regeneration;" reports that Meade has sent a copy of his review of Wilberforces's work on the incarnation which Meade attacks as "unscriptural and unprotestant."
  - William Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to the Editor of the Episcopal Recorder, n.p., 17 July 1850., 7 pages. ALS. Probably Draft. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Responds to a letter from an earlier edition of the Recorder in which an anonymous correspondent noted Meade's approbation of an essay by James Craik; quotes extensively from letter which he sent to Craik congratulating him on a sermon which Craik published on "Baptismal Regeneration"; supported Craik's view that the operations of the Holy Spirit were not contingent on baptism as supported by the reformers; takes exception to his "restricted an exclusive use of the term "regeneration"; argues that the Holy Spirit bestows gifts sovereignly; concludes that more good would be done concentrating on the Scriptures rather than searching for what the Fathers or Reformers wrote; on the whole, he argues that more success is to be found in preaching the plain Gospel of Christ to perishing sinners.
    Including printed leaflet of text. Taken from the Episcopal Recorder.
  - Bishop Philander Chase, Cincinatti, Ohio, to Rt. Rev. W[illiam] Meade, Virginia, 17 Oct[ober] 1850., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Requests him to preside at the consecration of Rev. Paine as the Bishop of Cape Palmas and its vicinity in Africa.
  - [Bishop William Whittingham, Baltimore, Maryland], to the Archbishops and Bishops of the Church of England, [27 December 1850]., 3 pages. Cy of L. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Expresses concern for the "recent encroachments and assaults upon that [the Anglican] Church;" refers to the Pope's establishing of the Catholic hierarchy as schismatical; refers to "embarrassments" [the conversions of Newman and Ware (?)], as having affected the "free action" of Anglican ministers in the discharge of the "highest spiritual trust"; urges them to "deliberate in solemn council for the preservation of the faith."
    Including TCy of L. 3 pages.
  - William Meade, to the Editors of the Protestant Churchman, n.p. [ca. 1850's]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Emphatically denies that he has ever introduced "political discussions into the pulpit"; reports that he doesn't even vote, so as not to offend anyone; believes politics to be inimical to piety; expresses fear whether the union of the Church [between North and South] can be maintained.
  - Samuel [?], Bishop of the Diocese of Oxford, [England], [ca. 1850 or 1851]., 1 page. PD. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Protests the division of England into dioceses by the Pope and the appointing of Catholic bishops to serve over those dioceses.
  Series 6: Correspondence, 1851-1860
- Correspondence, 1851-1860., 29 items. (Box-folder 2:2-4)
  - [William Meade], Millwood, [Virginia], to Bishop Whittingham [Bp. of Maryland], 3 January 1851., 6 pages. Cy of AL. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Suggests that Whittingham's proposal for an address to the English Bishops is ill-advised; even though the address would attack the "present assault" of the Roman see on the Church, the call for a convocation therein may aid rather than hinder the tractarians; declares that the American church should be grateful that it is not tied like the English church to be state; the English church could easily argue that the American [Episcopal] church's voluntary system is as open to appeal from Rome as the acts of the preceding [30] years had made the English church vulnerable.
    Including TCy of L. 5 pages.
  - [Rt. Rev.] W[illiam] R. Whittingham, Baltimore, [Maryland], to William Meade, n.p., 13 January 1851., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Requests that Meade endorse a document drafted by Bishop Brownell which would express the support of the American Episcopal Bishops for their Anglican brethren. Brownell's document [is more temperate than was Whittingham's, yet] still refers to the Pope's action as schismatical.
    Incl. 1 D, drafted by Bishop Brownell.
  - [William Meade], Millwood [Virginia], to [William R. Whittingham, Baltimore, Maryland], 18 Jan[uar]y 1851., 4 pages. Cy of S. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Explains that he cannot sign Brownell's circular; reports that he has not read the pope's "offensive document" and that the argument that the establishment of the hierarchy in England is schismatical would open the English to the same charge in Canada where the "Romanists predominate;" has drawn up his own letter which avoids some of the pitfalls of the others; requests that if approved it be transmitted to the Archbishop of Canterbury.
    Including TCy of L. 4 pages.
  - [William Meade], n.p. to the Archbishops and Bishops of the Protestant Episcopal Church of England, [ca. 18 Jan. 1851]., 4 pages. LS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Draft of letter under date 14 Feb[ruary] 1851.
    Including TCy of AL. 4 pages.
  - [Rt. Rev.] Philander Chase, to the Archbishop of Canterbury, 14 February 1851., 2 pages. Cy of LS. [prob. in the hand of a clerk]. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Explains that distance involved between American bishops is so great that it would almost be impossible to have all sign a letter; enclosed Meade's letter and hopes that this will evidence the concern of the American Bishops.
    Including TCy of L. 2 pages. Next item is an Enclosure to this one.
  - Phil[ander] Chase [signed L as presiding Bishop in America, drafted by William Meade], n.p. to the Archbishops and Bishops of the Protestant Episcopal Church of England, 14 Feb[ruary] 1851., 4 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Expresses concern that the Catholic Church has made an appeal to the English to return to the faith and expresses dismay over those in both Great Britain and the U.S. who have returned to the Roman Catholic communion; encourages them to be true to the principles of the primitive church and the Reformers; prays for grace for the English church.
    Including TCy of LS. 5 pages.
  - William Rollinson Whittingham, Baltimore, Maryland to the Bishops of the PEC in the U.S., 7 April 1851., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Protests to a letter signed "Philander Chase" addressed to the English and Irish clerical hierarchy; affirms that Chase's position as President in the House of Bishops does not entitle him to presume to speak for all the American bishops and most emphatically declares that he doesn't speak for him.
  - [Bishop] Philander Chase, Jubilee College, n.p., to William Meade, n.p., 29 April [1851]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Expresses sympathy for health problems; apologies for making any statement to cause Meade distress, particularly a reference to "extreme Calvinism;" writes that he knows not what effect Whittingham's protest will have; asks for advice.
    Including 1 TCy of ALS. 2 pages.
  - [William Meade], Millwood, [Virginia], to the Executive Committee of the Sunday School Union of the P.E. Church, n.p., 17 [September ?] 1851., 4 pages. AL. Draft (Box-folder 2:2)
    Accuses the Union of quoting him from a 1827 letter when he approved of their activity;' charges them, however, with increasing Tractarian support and expresses disapproval.
  - [Rt. Rev.] Manton Eastham, Boston, [Massachusetts], to W[illiam] Meade, n.p., 29 Sep[tember] 1851., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Will take no steps in the charges from New Jersey against Bishop Doane.
  - William Meade, Millwood, [Virginia] to [?], 16 December 1851., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Assures correspondent that he never intended to enter the Presbyterian ministry and that his friend Mr. Hill did not try to proselytize him but encouraged him to enter the Episcopal ministry.
  - W[illiam] Meade, June 1852., 2 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Declares that he was brought up in the Episcopal Church and that he had never had any design of entering the Presbyterian ministry.
  - [Rt. Rev.] C. P. M[cilvaine], Parish, [France], to William Meade, n.p., 28 May 1853., 4 pages. ALS (Box-folder 2:3)
    Relates his journeys through England and the occasion to speak from different pulpits which it afforded him; made the case for evangelicalism wherever he went; noted that the High Church there was high and dry; warns Meade "Don't let this [letter] go out of your hands."
  - W[illiam Meade], n.p., to Rev. Thos. Atkinson, n.p., 17 June [18]53., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Notes that correspondence between Meade and Atkinson has been of an official nature and not of a personal one because they differ in their views of church polity; fears that he is a tractarian; believes that he is not the worst choice for the Bishopric of North Carolina; informs him that he knows that many of the laity were opposed to the selection of anyone other than a Low Churchman; wished him well in the episcopate.
  - [William Meade], Millwood, [Virginia], to the Editor of the Calendar, n.p., 20 July 1853., 4 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Addresses the paper regarding two correspondents who had attacked a book as misleading which Meade had published containing extracts of J.M.'s [?] work on Baptismal Regeneration; argues that his design in publishing the book was to give an extract that was "as practical and useful as possible"; to have published the offending omitted passages would not have been "profitable" and would have been unrepresentative.
  - [William Meade], Millwood, [Virginia], to a minister [?], 25 July [18]53., 4 pages. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Expresses dismay over some of the errors which Wilberforce had fallen into in his History of the American Church, perhaps because of his remarks on slaveholders, to which the Southern Bishops objected; noted that English clergy might come to the General Convention in New York if invited, but that the invitation would be better if from a private individual or society; hopes no English clergy will come; affirms affection for England and the early influence of Wilberforce.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Winchester, Virginia, to Rev. J. A. Weed, Richmond, Virginia, 22 May [18]54., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Urges Weed, who has been attending Roman Catholic services to choose between the Episcopal and Roman Catholic churches; argues that since he was trained in an Episcopal seminary and has been preaching for ten years that he ought to choose between the two churches.
  - William Meade, King George Co., [Virginia], to [?], 20 June [18]54., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Informs correspondent that Bishop Whittingham warned Meade that he was injuring the Church by maintaining his association with the E. K. S. [Evangelical Knowledge Society] and that the E. K. S. had accused the Church of being corrupt; Meade argued that they had only noted that there was error in the church.
  - W[illiam] Meade, "Mountain View," [Millwood, Virginia], to Ann [?], 8 Decem[ber] [18]54., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Expresses a long-held desire that a commentary on certain portions of the Bible be prepared for slaves; sends personal regards.
  - Henry I. Whitehouse [Bishop of Illinois], Bloomington, Illinois, to [William] Meade, n.p., 30 April 1857., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)